Guide to the State College of Washington School of Mechanical Engineering Records 1913-1940
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
State College of Washington School of Mechanical Engineering Records
1913-1940
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Archives 374
State College of Washington. Department of Mechanical Engineering.
4 linear feet of shelf space 4 boxes
This collection contains documents generated by Washington State College’s (later Washington State University’s) Mechanical Engineering Department from the 1910s to 1940. The majority of this collection is about the projects planned and/or undertaken by the Mechanical Engineering Department during these years. Professors, and eventually department chairs, A.C. Abell and Howard Langdon gathered or authored much of the research found in this collection. This collection also includes departmental faculty correspondence as well as records of various student activities and Depression-era federal funding requirements and opportunities for Mechanical Engineering students.
Mechanical Engineering courses were offered at Washington State College (WSC) from the school’s beginning in the 1890s. In 1917-1918, the Department of Mechanical and Electrical Engineering was incorporated into the College of Mechanic Arts and Engineering during a WSC reorganization. By the time Professor Howard Langdon became department chair in 1933, the College of Mechanic Arts and Engineering had officially separated. Langdon replaced Professor A.C. Abell as Mechanical Engineering department chair following Abell’s sudden death from paralysis on December 31, 1932. Langdon served as chair until 1944.
Prior to his death, Abell had gathered research and taken notes on designing and operating a new power plant for WSC. Both before and after Abell’s death, Langdon contributed to this research. In late 1933, the Mechanical Engineering Department was placed in charge of designing, writing specifications for, and supervising the installation of a new power plant at WSC, replacing the power plant that had heated the campus for nearly thirty years. Langdon served as the Chief Engineer for the design and construction of the new power plant. Funded by the New Deal’s Works Progress Administration (WPA), the power plant began operating on October 25, 1935 and the WPA contract for the project was deemed officially complete on December 1, 1935.
During this same period, two other New Deal programs assisted the Department of Mechanical Engineering. From 1933-1935, selected students received funding to stay at WSC through the Federal Emergency Relief Administration (FERA). The National Youth Administration (NYA) replaced FERA following the 1935 enactment of the WPA. Like FERA, the NYA provided work-study programs for selected college students throughout the United States, including WSC’s Mechanical Engineering students. Both programs intended to prevent students from dropping out of school and flooding the job market. These federal programs helped the Mechanical Engineering department survive the Depression, providing necessary funding for student tuition, jobs, and campus projects.
This collection consists primarily of documents such as blueprints, photos, data diagrams, materials testing lab books, and research papers detailing the research and projects of WSC’s Mechanical Engineering Department. Most of these projects took place on WSC’s campus although a few projects were undertaken by the department on behalf of off-campus entities, including local high schools, hospitals, and companies. Materials dedicated to the design and installation of the 1930s WPA-funded campus power plant figure largely in this collection, with research for the proposed power plant beginning in the 1920s.
Additionally, the collection contains correspondence between WSC Mechanical Engineering faculty and students needing federal aid in order to continue attending college during the Great Depression as well as the federal relief project sheets used to create and track the work-study opportunities provided to selected students. This collection also includes papers and pre-written dialogue for bi-weekly radio talks in the 1930s that shared the latest research of Mechanical Engineering faculty as well as updates on student activities. Other materials provide the minutes, programs, and activities generated by Mechanical Engineering students and their faculty sponsors in Sigma Xi, Phi Kappa Phi, the American Society of Mechanical Engineers, and the Student Activity Committee. There are also materials from the 1937 glider accident during which two Mechanical Engineering students, Cloyd Artman and Frank See, were killed during a demonstration in front of the WSC Aero Club (headed by Professor Howard Langdon). Letters, witness testimonies, newspaper reports, and photos of the crash scene are included among these materials.
This collection also contains a substantial amount of faculty correspondence, largely generated by Professor Howard Langdon during his tenure as department chair and covering a variety of topics including his own research, department issues, changes in curriculum, and student matters.
This collection is arranged in two series.
Series 1 is arranged into two subseries, each arranged alphabetically. Subseries 1.1 consists of materials on WSC’s power plants. Some of this material describes additions and revisions made during the 1920s to the decades-old power plant, but most of the material is either research to develop a new power plant or materials describing the designing and building of the WPA-funded power plant in the mid-1930s. Subseries 1.2 consists of materials on general research performed by the Mechanical Engineering Department in WSC’s Machine Shop and Materials Testing Laboratory.
Series 2 is arranged into two subseries, each arranged alphabetically. Subseries 2.1 contains materials pertaining to Mechanical Engineering faculty, including correspondence, faculty research reports, and faculty participation in community clubs such as Pullman’s Kiwanis Club. Subseries 2.2 contains materials pertaining largely to Mechanical Engineering students. These materials consist primarily of paperwork from a variety of student clubs, programs, committees, and societies.
This collection is open and available for research use.
The materials in this collection were transferred to the Washington State University Libraries’ Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections on December 14, 1988 by the WSU Architecture School and retained as accession UA88-47.
This collection was separated from other materials in UA 88-47 during processing. These other records contain materials from Washington State College’s Architectural Engineering department from the 1920s through the 1950s (Archives 375).
They also contain materials generated by Washington State College’s architect Stanley Smith through his WSC campus projects and his private practice projects from the 1920s-1940s (Cage 888).
Mechanical Arts and Engineering College Records, 1892-1943 (Archives 156)
Mechanical Engineering Department Records, 1910-1976 (Archives 31).
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
State College of Washington. Department of Mechanical Engineering -- History; State College of Washington. Department of Mechanical and Electrical Engineering -- History; State College of Washington. Department of Mechanical and Electrical Engineering
Mechanical engineering -- History
Colleges and Universities; Washington (State)
- Series 1: Research Files
  - Subseries 1.1: Washington State College Power Plant
    - Blueprint, Forced Draft Unit, Washington State College, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Blueprint, Water Tube Boilers, Washington State College, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Boilers, General, Washington State College, 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Boiler Test Data, Washington State College Power Plant, 1926-1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Calculations for Proposed Steam Plant, Deck Beam Calculations, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Charts for Flow of Water in Pipes, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Coal Weighing, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Coal Weighing Devices, 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Condensers, Heat Transfers, 1919-1931 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Condensers, Temperature Notes and Research, 1913-1928 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Heat Exchange Research (Langdon), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Heating, Research, Drawings, Blueprints, 1927-1937 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Heating Schedule Data, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Heating, Temperature Data, 1927-1937 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Piping, Cost Data, Etc., 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Power Plant, Misc., 1932-1934 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - WSC Power Plant Stokers, Westinghouse Electric & Manufacturing Co. Blueprints, Contracts, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - WSC Power Plant Stokers, Westinghouse Electric & Manufacturing Co. Correspondence, Contracts, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Pulverized Coal Systems, Correspondence and Data, 1927-1932 (Box 1, Folder 19-20)
    - Pumps, 1928-1931 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Pumps, Data, Blueprints, and Correspondence, 1934-1936 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Refractories, Correspondence and Research Materials, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Sketches and Blueprints, Boilers and Auxiliary Equipment, Washington State College, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Steam Delivery Charges Data, 1927-1931 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Steam Distribution Data and Research Papers (A.C. Abell), 1928-1931 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Steam Distribution Data and Research Papers (A.C. Abell), 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Steam Load Data, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Steam, Research Book, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Steam/Turbine Cost, Delivery, Temperature Data (A.C. Abell), Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Total Electrical Load Data (A.C. Abell), 1930 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Vacuum Vent Valve Blueprint/Design, 1927-1937 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - WSC Hydro-Jet System Blueprints, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Welders' Qualification Records (Power Plant Equipment), 1935 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Welders' Test (Power Plant Equipment, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Subseries 1.2: General Research
    - Annual Report, Amalgamated Fuel Burners Union, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Auto-Engines' Class Notes (A.C. Abell), Undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Blueprint, Beam loads, Washington State College, Undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Blueprint, First Floor, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Concrete Costs, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Data and Equipment Correspondence, 1927-1930 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Data and Equipment Correspondence, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Extensometer and Compressometer (Hydro-Static) WSC Research, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Fan Motors and Drivers, Gymnasium, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Francis Adams High School, Blueprints, Consultation, and Sketches, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Franklin Grade School Heating Calculations, Pullman, WA, Undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Fuel, Correspondence and Research, 1930-1932 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Fuel, Correspondence and Research, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Heating Costs, Commons Building; Troy Hall, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Heating, Morrill Hall Blueprints, 1914-1920 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Heating Plant Research (Langdon; Mechanical Engineering Dept.), 1932-1938 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Heating Research, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Heating and Ventilation, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - High Temp. Testing of Metals, Blueprints, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Infiltration of Air in Buildings, Misc., 1921 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Laboratory Observations, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Materials Testing Correspondence, 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Materials Testing Correspondence, 1929-1932 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Materials Testing Field Data, Public Works Administration, 1934-1936 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Materials Testing Field Data, Public Works Administration, 1934-1938 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Materials Testing Field Data, Public Works Administration, 1936-1938 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Materials Testing Lab Book, Alloy and Mild Steels, 1931-1934 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Materials Testing Lab Book, Concrete, 1927-1928 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Materials Testing Lab Book, Concrete, 1928-1929 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
    - Materials Testing Lab Book, Concrete, 1928-1929 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Materials Testing Lab Book, Concrete, 1929-1932 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Materials Testing Lab Book, Concrete, 1930-1932 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Materials Testing Laboratory Data, Concrete Compression, 1929-1930 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Measuring Device, WSC Research, 1927-1928 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Refrigeration and Insulation Data, WSC, 1925-1932 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - State Hospital, Medical Lake, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Steam Laboratory Observations, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Stoker Research (Roslyn Cascade Coal Co.), 1930-1938 (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
    - Temperature and Wind Velocities, Pullman, WA, 1912-1921 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Testing Research, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Unfinished Projects, Washington State College, 1927-1935 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Weather Conditions over a Ten Year Period, Pullman, WA, Undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Series 2: Administrative materials
  - Subseries 2.1: Mechanical Engineering faculty
    - Correspondence, Catalog Changes, Sample Testing, 1932-1936 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Kiwanis Correspondence, 1935-1936 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Kiwanis Correspondence, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Letters, General, 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Library and Staff Correspondence, 1934-1939 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Staff Letters, 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - General Correspondence, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Curriculum Changes, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Faculty Research Report, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Subseries 2.2: Mechanical Engineering students
    - American Society of Mechanical Engineering, 5th Annual Pacific Northwest Student Conference, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
    - ASME Contact and Membership Correspondence, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - ASME Correspondence (General), 1940 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - ASME Luncheon and Dinner, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - ASME Program Material and Address List, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Civil Works Administration (CWA) Student Employment, 1933-1934 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Glider Accident, Cloyd Artman and Frank See, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Federal Emergency Relief Administration (FERA), 1934 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Federal Emergency Relief Administration (FERA) and the National Youth Administration (NYA), 1935 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - National Youth Administration, 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - National Youth Administration, 1937-1939 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Prospective Students (Dept. of Mech. Eng.), 1936-1939 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
    - Radio Talks, Department of Mechanical Engineering, 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 12-14)
    - Senior Inspection Trip, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Sigma Xi Correspondence, 1936-1938 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Sigma Xi and Phi Kappa Phi, 1929-1938 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Student Activities Committee, 1936-1938 (Box 4, Folder 18-19)